<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0" xml:id="chap-words">
    <title>Words</title>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-words-intro">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            Words are the most fundamental building blocks of our language. Although they may look
            simple on the surface, they are very ingenious devices that pack not only meaning, but
            also grammatical information. For our purposes, we will say that a words consists of a
                <emphasis>stem</emphasis> and <emphasis>affixes</emphasis>. Let's look at three
            simple sentences: </para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>I <emphasis role="bold">walk</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>John <emphasis role="bold">walk</emphasis>s.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Jack <emphasis role="bold">walk</emphasis>ed. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            All three sentences contain some 'form' of
            <emphasis>walk</emphasis>. We say that these instances are all
            <emphasis>inflections</emphasis> of the verb
            <emphasis>walk</emphasis>. The part of the inflections that is
            shared (<emphasis>walk</emphasis>) is what we call the
            <emphasis>stem</emphasis>. The parts that are not common are named
            <emphasis>affixes</emphasis>. We inflect verbs to indicate tense
            (present, past, etc.), the person of the verb's subject (first,
            second, and third person), and the number (singular or plural). The
            affix <emphasis>s</emphasis> in John walk<emphasis>s</emphasis>,
            for instance, tells us (in combination with the subject John) that
            the verb <emphasis>walk</emphasis> is in present tense, third
            person singular.
        </para>
        <para>
            Other types of words have inflections as well. For example, we
            inflect nouns to distinguish singular and plural:
        </para>
        <para>
            I saw one <emphasis role="bold">duck</emphasis>. I saw two
            <emphasis role="bold">duck</emphasis>s.
        </para>
        <para>
            Up to this point, we have just seen one kind of affix: one that is
            glued to the end of the word. There are actually many kinds of
            affixes. For now, you should only know about two:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para> Prefix: appears in front of the stem. For example, <emphasis role="bold"
                            >un</emphasis>believable. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Suffix: appears after the stem. For example, duck<emphasis role="bold"
                        >s</emphasis>. </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            Now, with that out of the way, let's get some work done.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-words-playwords">
        <title>Playing with words</title>
        <para>
            Written words consist of characters. We can write down characters
            in Haskell with single quotes. If you type in a character in
            <emphasis>ghci</emphasis>, it will simply echo back the character:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> 'h'
'h'</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            This is all that <emphasis>ghci</emphasis> does, it evaluates
            whatever you type. A character evaluates to... a character. We
            confirm that Haskell agrees with us that this actually a character
            by asking the type with <emphasis>:type</emphasis> or its shorthand
            <emphasis>:t</emphasis>:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :t 'h'
'h' :: Char    </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Great. Haskell indeed confirms that 'h' is a character, or in
            Haskell's words of type <emphasis>Char</emphasis>. Not all that
            practical with the small amount of single-lettered words in English
            though. Rather than a single character, we want a sequence of
            characters. Not surprisingly, Haskell has a data types to build
            sequences. The most commonly used sequence is the list. You can
            have lists of many things: lists of groceries, lists of planets,
            and lists of characters. We can make a literal list in Haskell by
            enumerating its elements, separated by commas and surrounded by
            square brackets. For instance, the list
            <emphasis>1, 2, 3, 4, 5</emphasis> is written as
            <emphasis>[1, 2, 3, 4, 5]</emphasis>. Let's try to make a list of
            characters:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> ['h','e','l','l','o']
"hello" </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Now we are getting somewhere! Let's look at the type of this list:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :t ['h','e','l','l','o']
['h','e','l','l','o'] :: [Char] </screen>
        </para>
        <para>Its type is <emphasis>[Char]</emphasis>, which should be read as 'list of characters'.
            Such a list of characters is known as <emphasis>a string</emphasis> Of course, writing
            down words in this manner is not very convenient. Fortunately, as the second to last
            example already suggests, there is a more convenient notation: wrap the characters in
            double quotes: </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> "hello"
"hello"
Prelude> :type "hello"
"hello" :: [Char] </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            We will take this opportunity to seriously demolish some words, but
            all with the noble cause of learning some commonly-used Haskell
            list functions. The first function <function>length</function>
            returns the length of a list:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> length "hello"
5
Prelude> length [1,2,3]
3 </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            To get a better impression of functions, it is often useful to look
            at its type:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type length
length :: [a] -> Int </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            That's one heck of a type! Basically, it says 'give me a list of
            something (denoted by the <emphasis>a</emphasis> between the list
            brackets), then I will give you an Int'. In these so-called
            <emphasis>type signatures</emphasis>, letters that are not
            capitalized are generic, meaning that they can be of some
            unspecified type. Consequently, <emphasis>[a]</emphasis> is a list
            with elements of some type. <emphasis role="bold">But:</emphasis>
            all elements should be of the same type. An
            <emphasis>Int</emphasis> is an integral number: a positive or
            negative whole number.
        </para>
        <para>
            Two other basic list functions are <function>head</function> and
            <function>tail</function>. <function>head</function> returns the
            first element of a list, <function>tail</function> everything but
            the first element:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> head "hello"
'h'
Prelude> tail "hello"
"ello"</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            The type of head is the following:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type head
head :: [a] -> a
            </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Hey, two <emphasis>a</emphasis>'s! Equipped with the knowledge we
            have, we know that <function>head</function> is a function that
            takes a list of something, and gives back something. But there is
            an additional constraint here: although <emphasis>a</emphasis> is
            some type, all <emphasis>a</emphasis>'s have to be the same type.
            So, applying <function>head</function> to a list of numbers gives a
            number, applying <function>head</function> to a list of characters
            gives a character, etc.
        </para>
        <para>
            The type of <function>tail</function> should now be easy to
            understand:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type tail
tail :: [a] -> [a] </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            We apply <function>tail</function> to a list of some type, and get
            back a list with the same type.
        </para>
        <para>
            Finally, the last function for now is <function>reverse</function>.
            We have to admit presenting this function with a bit of joy, since
            it will allow us to write our first little useful Haskell program.
            As expected, <function>reverse</function> reverses the elements of
            a list:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> reverse "hello"
"olleh"</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Olé! And another one:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> reverse "level"
"level"</screen>
        </para>
        <para>We bumped into a <function>palindrome</function>, a word that can be read forward and
            backward. Now, suppose we would like to write our own function to determine wether a
            word is a palindrome? We first need to make a slightly more abstract definition of a
            palindrome: a word is a palindrome if it is equal to its reverse. In Haskell we can
            compare values using the <function>==</function> operator: </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> "hello" == "hello"
True
Prelude> "hello" == "olleh"
False </screen>
        </para>
        <para>Such a comparison evaluates to <emphasis>True</emphasis> if both values are equal, or
            to <emphasis>False</emphasis> in case they are not. <emphasis>True</emphasis> and
                <emphasis>False</emphasis> are the only values of the <emphasis>Bool</emphasis>
            type. Since <function>reverse</function> also returns a value, nothing holds us from
            using it in comparisons: </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> "hello" == reverse "hello"
False
Prelude> "level" == reverse "level"
True </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            The test that we devised for detecting palindromes seems to work.
            But it is a lot of typing. We can generalize this into a function.
            Let's replace both words by the symbolic name
            <emphasis>word</emphasis> (but don't execute this in
            <emphasis role="bold">ghci</emphasis> yet, since it does not know
            this symbolic name):
        </para>
        <screen>word == reverse word </screen>
        <para>
            Let's do some magic:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> let palindrome word = word == reverse word </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            This defines the function <function>palindrome</function> taking
            one argument, and binds this argument to the symbolic name
            <emphasis>word</emphasis>. To this function we assign the
            expression <emphasis>word == reverse word</emphasis>. Play a little
            with this function to be convinced that it actually works. Some
            examples:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> palindrome "hello"
False
Prelude> palindrome "level"
True
Prelude> palindrome "racecar"
True </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            If this function is still a mystery to you, it may be useful two
            write out application of the function stepwise, for a word that is
            not a palindrome:
        </para>
        <screen>palindrome "hello"
palindrome "hello" = "hello" == reverse "hello"
palindrome "hello" = "hello" == "olleh"
palindrome "hello" = False     </screen>
        <para>
            and a word that <emphasis>is</emphasis> a palindrome:
        </para>
        <screen>palindrome "racecar"
palindrome "racecar" = "racecar" == reverse "racecar"
palindrome "racecar" = "racecar" == "racecar"
palindrome "racecar" = True</screen>
        <para>
            Congratulations, you have made your first function, which is in
            essence a small program!
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-words-to-sentences">
        <title>From words to sentences</title>
        <para>
            So far, we have looked at words in isolation. However, in language,
            words are often combined to form a higher level of meaning
            representation: a sentence. Provided what we have learned about
            representing words in Haskell, the step towards representing
            sentences should be a minor one. We could, for example, represent
            sentences in the exactly the same way we represented words:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> "The cat is on the mat."
"The cat is on the mat." </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            That's fine for a beginning, although not so convenient. Let us see
            why. Assume we ask you to give us the first word of a sentence? In
            the previous section, we learned that <function>head</function> can
            be used to get the first element of a list. Let's try to apply that
            here:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> head "The cat is on the mat."
'T' </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            As you probably expected, that didn't work. We represented a
            sentence as a list of characters (a string), and hence asking for
            the first element will give the first character. But wait! What if
            we represented a sentence as a list of words?
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> ["The", "cat", "is", "on", "the", "mat", "."]
["The","cat","is","on","the","mat","."]
Prelude> :type ["The", "cat", "is", "on", "the", "mat", "."]
["The", "cat", "is", "on", "the", "mat", "."] :: [[Char]]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Nifty! We just constructed a list, of a list of characters. Though,
            you may wonder why we made the punctation at the end of the
            sentence a separate word. This is mostly a pragmatic choice,
            because gluing this punctuation sign to <emphasis>mat</emphasis>
            does not really form a word either. Having the period sign separate
            is more practical for future processing. Hence, formally we say
            that a sentence consists of tokens, where a token can be a word, a
            number, and a punctuation sign.
        </para>
        <para>
            Rinse and repeat:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> head ["The", "cat", "is", "on", "the", "mat", "."]
"The"</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Since a word is also a list, we can apply a function to words as
            well. For example, we can get the first character of the first word
            by applying <function>head</function>, to the
            <function>head</function> of a sentence:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> head (head ["The", "cat", "is", "on", "the", "mat", "."])
'T'</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Note that we need parenthesis to force Haskell to evaluate the part
            in parentheses first. If we do not enforce this order of
            evaluation, Haskell will try to evaluate
            <emphasis>head head</emphasis> first, which makes no sense.
            Remember that <function>head</function> requires a list as its
            argument, and <function>head</function> is not a list.
        </para>
        <para>
            Now that we know how to represent sentence, this is a good time to
            try to write yet another small program. This time, we will write a
            function to compute the average token length in a corpus (a
            collection of texts, not a part of an organ). Since we did not look
            at real corpora yet, pick any sentence you like as
            <emphasis>My First Corpus</emphasis>™. The authors will use
            <emphasis>&quot;Oh, no, flying pink ponies.&quot;</emphasis> The
            average token length is the sum of the lengths of all tokens,
            divided by the number of tokens. So, stepwise, we have to:
        </para>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Get the length of each token in the corpus.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Sum the lengths of the tokens.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Divide the sum by the length of the corpus.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
            You know how to get the in characters length of a single token:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> length "flying"
6</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Since you are lazy (and if not, you should spend more time on your
            girlfriend!), you are not going to apply
            <function>length</function> token by token manually. Moreover, in
            our final function, this will not work anyway, since we do not know
            the length of the sentence beforehand (how nice, Haskell wants us
            to be lazy). Instead we want to say to Haskell &quot;Hey Haskell!
            Please apply this length function to each element of the
            list.&quot; It turns out that Haskell has a function to do this
            called <function>map</function>. Time to inspect
            <function>map</function>:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type map
map :: (a -> b) -> [a] -> [b]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            And we are in for another surprise. The most surprising element is
            probably the first element in the type signature,
            <emphasis>(a -&gt; b)</emphasis>. Also surprising is that we now
            see three types, <emphasis>(a -&gt; b)</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>[a]</emphasis> and <emphasis>[b]</emphasis>. The latter
            is simple: this function takes two arguments,
            <emphasis>(a -&gt; b)</emphasis> and <emphasis>[a]</emphasis>, and
            returns <emphasis>[b]</emphasis>. <emphasis>(a -&gt; b)</emphasis>
            as the notation suggests, is a function taking an
            <emphasis>a</emphasis> and returning a <emphasis>b</emphasis>. So,
            <function>map</function> is actually a function that takes a
            function as its argument, or in functional programming-speak: a
            <emphasis>higher order</emphasis> function.
        </para>
        <para>
            So, <function>map</function> is a function that takes a function
            that maps from <emphasis>a</emphasis> to <emphasis>b</emphasis>,
            takes a list of <emphasis>a</emphasis>s, and returns a list of
            <emphasis>b</emphasis>s. That looks a suspiciously lot like what we
            want! We have a list of tokens represented as strings, the function
            length that takes a list and returns its length as an integer, and
            we want to have a list of integers representing the lengths. Looks
            like we have a winner!
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> map length ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", "flying", ",", "pink", "ponies"]
[2,1,2,1,6,1,4,6]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            We have now completed our first step: we have the length of each
            token in the corpus. Next, we have to sum the lengths that we have
            just retrieved. Fortunately, Haskell has a <function>sum</function>
            function:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type sum
sum :: (Num a) => [a] -> a</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Ok, sum takes a list of <emphasis>a</emphasis>s, and returns an
            <emphasis>a</emphasis>. But where did the
            <emphasis>(Num a) =&gt;</emphasis> come from? Well,
            <emphasis>Num</emphasis> is a so-called typeclass. A type can
            belong to one or more of such typeclasses. But belonging to a
            typeclass does not come without cost. In fact, it requires that
            certain functions need to be defined for types that belong to it.
            For instance, the typeclass <emphasis>Num</emphasis> is a typeclass
            for numbers, which requires amongst others, functions that define
            addition or subtraction. Coming back to the type signature,
            <function>sum</function> will sum a list of
            <emphasis>a</emphasis>s, but not just any <emphasis>a</emphasis>s,
            only those that belong to the typeclass <emphasis>Num</emphasis>.
            And after all, this makes sense, doesn't it? We cannot sum strings
            or planets, but we can sum numbers. In fact, we can only sum
            numbers.
        </para>
        <para>
            After this solemn introduction into typeclasses, feel free to take
            a cup of tea (or coffee, as one of the authors prefers), and try
            step two:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> sum (map length ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", "flying", ",", "pink", "ponies"])
23</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            By now, you will probably smell victory. The only step that remains
            is to divide the sum by the length of the sentence using the
            division operator (<emphasis>/</emphasis>):
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> sum (map length ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", "flying", ",", "pink", "ponies"]) /
  length ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", "flying", ",", "pink", "ponies"]

&lt;interactive>:1:0:
    No instance for (Fractional Int)
      arising from a use of `/' at &lt;interactive>:1:0-136
    Possible fix: add an instance declaration for (Fractional Int)
    In the expression:
          sum (map length ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", ....])
        / length ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", ....]
    In the definition of `it':
        it = sum (map length ["Oh", ",", "no", ....])
           / length ["Oh", ",", "no", ....]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            I hope you poured yourself a cup of herb tea! (or alternatively:
            espresso!) While this is all a bit cryptic, the second line
            (<emphasis>No instance for (Fractional Int)</emphasis>) gives some
            idea where this comes from. <emphasis>Fractional</emphasis> is
            typeclass for fractional numbers, and Haskell complains that Int is
            not defined to be of the typeclass <emphasis>Fractional</emphasis>.
            This sounds obvious, since an integer is not a fractional number.
            In other words, Haskell is trying to tell us that there is an
            <emphasis>Int</emphasis> in some place where it expected a type
            belonging to the typeclass <emphasis>Fractional</emphasis>. Since
            the division is the only new component, it is the first suspect of
            the breakdown:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type (/)
(/) :: (Fractional a) => a -> a -> a</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            First off, we put the division operator in parentheses. We have
            done this because the division operator is used as a so-called
            <emphasis>infix function</emphasis>: it is a function that is put
            between its arguments (like <emphasis>1.0 / 2.0</emphasis>). By
            putting an infix operator in parentheses, you are stating that you
            would like to use it as a regular function. This means you can do
            things like this:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> (/) 1.0 2.0
0.5</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Anyway, the verdict of the typesignature of
            <function>(/)</function> is clear, it requires two arguments that
            belong to the <emphasis>Fractional</emphasis> typeclass. The sum
            and length that we calculated clearly do not belong to this
            typeclass, since they are of the type <emphasis>Int</emphasis>:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type sum (map length ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", "flying", ",", "pink", "ponies"])
sum (map length ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", "flying", ",", "pink", "ponies"])
  :: Int
Prelude> :type length ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", "flying", ",", "pink", "ponies"]
length ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", "flying", ",", "pink", "ponies"]
  :: Int</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Fortunately, Haskell provides the function
            <function>fromIntegral</function> that converts an integer to any
            kind of number. Add <function>fromIntegral</function>, and you
            surely do get the average token length of the corpus:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> fromIntegral (sum (map length ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", "flying", ",", "pink", "ponies"])) /
  fromIntegral (length ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", "flying", ",", "pink", "ponies"])
2.875</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Well, that was a bumpier ride than you may have expected. Don't
            worry! During our first forays into Haskell, we were convinced that
            were too stupid for this too (and here we are writing a book).
            However, after more practice, you will learn that Haskell is
            actually a very simple and logical language.
        </para>
        <para>
            Maybe it will feel more like a victory after generalizing this to a
            function. You can follow the same pattern as in the palindrome
            example: replace the sentence with a symbolic name and transform it
            into a function:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> let averageLength l = fromIntegral (sum (map length l)) / fromIntegral (length l)
Prelude> averageLength ["Oh", ",", "no", ",", "flying", ",", "pink" ,"ponies"]
2.875</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Congratulations, you just wrote your second function! But wait, you
            actually accomplished more than you may expect. Check the type
            signature of <function>averageLength</function>.
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type averageLength
averageLength :: (Fractional b) => [[a]] -> b</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            You made your first weird type signature. Show it off to your
            colleague, significant other, or dog.
            <function>averageLength</function> is a function that takes a list
            of a list of <emphasis>a</emphasis>, and returns a
            <emphasis>b</emphasis> that belongs to the
            <emphasis>Fractional</emphasis> typeclass. But wait,
            <emphasis>a</emphasis> can be anything, right? What happens if we
            apply this function to a list of sentences?
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> averageLength [["I", "like", "Haskell", "."],
  ["Ruby", "rocks", "the", "too", "."],
  ["Who", "needs", "Java", "?"]]
4.333333333333333</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            That's the average sentence length, expressed in number of words.
            It turns out that, although we set out to make a function to
            calculate the average token length, we wrote a function that
            calculates the average length of lists in a list (e.g., characters
            in words, words in sentences, or sentences in a text). This happens
            very often when you write Haskell programs: lots of functions are
            generic and can be reused for other tasks.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-words-tokenization">
        <title>A note on tokenization</title>
        
        <para>When dealing with real-world text, it is usually not neatly split in sentences and
            tokens. For example, consider this book - punctuation is usually glued to words. These
            processes, sentence splitting and tokenization may seem trivial, unfortunately they are
            not. Consider the following sentence: </para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">E.g. Jack doesn't have 19.99 to spend. </emphasis></para>
        <para>
            If we simply perform sentence splitting on periods
            (<emphasis>.</emphasis>), we will find four sentences:
        </para>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>E.</emphasis>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>g.</emphasis>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Jack doesn't have 19.</emphasis>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>99 to spend.</emphasis>
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
            Of course, it is just one sentence. Similar problems arise during
            punctuation: how do we know that <emphasis>E.g.</emphasis> and
            <emphasis>19.99</emphasis> should not be split? And how about
            <emphasis>doesn't</emphasis>, which should probably be split as
            <emphasis>does n't</emphasis> or <emphasis>does not</emphasis>?
            Tokenization can be performed accurately, but it requires
            techniques that you will see in later chapters. So, we will come
            back to tokenization later. We promise!
        </para>
        <para>
            Of course, up to the point where we handle tokenization, we need
            material to work on. To make life easier for you, the material for
            the first chapters of the book is pre-tokenized in a plain-text
            file using two simple rules:
        </para>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    One sentence per line.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Tokens are separated by a space.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
            To convert a text file to a Haskell representation, sentence
            splitting is a matter of splitting by line, and tokenization
            splitting by space. Have a look at the following example:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> "This is Jack .\nHe is a Haskeller ."
"This is Jack .\nHe is a Haskeller ."</screen>
        </para>
        <para> This is exactly the representation that we will be using for our textual data. As you
            can see, the tokens are separated by spaces. Both sentences are separated using a
            newline. When writing down a string literally, you can insert a newline using <emphasis
                role="italic">\n</emphasis>. </para>
        <para>
            Haskell provides a <function>lines</function> function to split up
            a string by line. Not surprisingly, this function accepts a string
            as its first argument, and will return a list of strings:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type lines
lines :: String -> [String]
Prelude> lines "This is Jack .\nHe is a Haskeller ."
["This is Jack .","He is a Haskeller ."]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            That was easy! Now to the actual tokenization. For all sentences,
            we have a string representing the sentence. We want to split this
            string on the space character. Haskell also has a function to do
            this, named <function>words</function>. <function>words</function>
            is nearly the same function as <function>lines</function>, except
            that it splits on spaces rather than newlines:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> words "This is Jack ."
["This","is","Jack","."]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            That will do, but we have to apply this to every sentence in the
            list of sentences. Recall that we can use the
            <function>map</function> function we have seen earlier to apply the
            <function>words</function> function to each element of the list of
            (untokenized) sentences:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> map words (lines "This is Jack .\nHe is a Haskeller .")
[["This","is","Jack","."],["He","is","a","Haskeller","."]]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Allright! That will do the job. We know how to turn this into a
            full-fledged function:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> let splitTokenize text = map words (lines text)
Prelude> splitTokenize "This is Jack .\nHe is a Haskeller ."
[["This","is","Jack","."],["He","is","a","Haskeller","."]]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            This is a good moment to beautify this function a bit. To make it
            simpler, we first need to get rid of the parentheses. We use the
            parentheses to tell Haskell that it should evaluate
            <emphasis>lines text</emphasis> first, or otherwise it will try to
            map over the function <function>lines</function>, which will fail,
            because it is not a list. Very often, you will encounter function
            applications of the form <emphasis>f(g(x))</emphasis>, or
            <emphasis>f(g(h(x)))</emphasis>, etc. Haskell provides the
            <emphasis>(.)</emphasis> function to combine such function
            applications. So, <emphasis>f(g(x))</emphasis> can be rewritten to
            <emphasis>(f . g) x</emphasis> (apply function
            <emphasis>f</emphasis> to the outcome of <emphasis>g(x)</emphasis>)
            and <emphasis>f(g(h(x)))</emphasis> as
            <emphasis>(f . g . h) x</emphasis> (apply function
            <emphasis>f</emphasis> to the outcome of a function
            <emphasis>g</emphasis>, which is in turn applied to the outcome of
            <emphasis>h(x)). As you can see, this so-called</emphasis>function
            composition* makes things much easier to read. We can now rewrite
            our tokenization function by using function composition:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> let splitTokenize text = (map words . lines) text</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            This states that we apply <emphasis>map words</emphasis> to the
            outcome <emphasis>lines text</emphasis>. This may not yet seem so
            interesting. However, it allows us to make yet another
            simplification step. Consider the type of the
            <function>map</function> function:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type map
map :: (a -> b) -> [a] -> [b]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            <function>map</function> takes a function, and a list, and returns
            a list. Now we will do something that may look weird, but is very
            common in functional programming.
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type map words
map words :: [String] -> [[String]]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Applying <function>map</function> to just one argument will give...
            another function! What we just did is to bind just one argument of
            the map function, and that gives another function that has
            implicitly bound that argument. This process is called
            <emphasis>currying</emphasis> (indeed, named after the
            mathematician Haskell Curry) in functional programming slang.
        </para>
        <para>
            If we look back at our <function>splitTokenize</function> function,
            and look up the type of <emphasis>map words . lines</emphasis>, we
            see that it is a function that takes a <emphasis>String</emphasis>
            and returns a list of a list of strings:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type map words . lines
map words . lines :: String -> [[String]]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            In our function body, we apply this function to the argument
            <emphasis>text</emphasis>. Of course, this is not really necessary,
            because <emphasis>map words . lines</emphasis> already defines our
            function (as we have shown above). We just need to bind this to the
            name <function>splitTokenize</function>. Consequently the function
            can once more be simplified:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>splitTokenize :: String -> [[String]]
Prelude> splitTokenize "This is Jack .\nHe is a Haskeller ."
[["This","is","Jack","."],["He","is","a","Haskeller","."]]
{% endhighlight %}</screen>
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-words-lists">
        <title>Word lists</title>
        <para>
            In the following two sections, we will introduce two prototypical
            tasks related words. The first is to make a word (or actually
            token) list,the second task is making a word frequency.
        </para>
        <para>
            A word list is a very simple data structure: it is just a list of
            <emphasis>unique</emphasis> words or tokens that occur in a text.
            Our corpus is also just a list of words, but since it contains
            duplicates, it is not a word list. The obvious method to make a
            word list is to go through a corpus word by word, and adding words
            that we did not see yet to a second list. This requires some
            functions we haven't seen yet:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Adding an element to a list.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Checking whether an element is (or is not) in a list.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Constructing a list while traversing another list.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            We like easy things first, so let's start with the first item:
            adding an element to a list. We have seen the
            <function>head</function> function before that chops of the head of
            the list and returns it. But we can also do the reverse: take a
            list and give it a new head. The old head then becomes the head of
            the tail (are you still following?). In Haskell, we can do this
            using the <function>(:)</function> function:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> 2 : [3,4,5]
[2,3,4,5] </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Ain't that great? We can also add a head, and yet another:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> 1 : 2 : [3,4,5]
[1,2,3,4,5] </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            What if we do not have an element yet? Add the head to the empty
            list (<emphasis>[]</emphasis>):
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> "Hi" : []
["Hi"] </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            With that covered, the next thing we need to be able to do is
            checking whether some element belongs to a list. We can do this
            using the <function>elem</function> function. It takes an element
            as its first argument, and a list as its second. It will return a
            Bool of the value <emphasis>True</emphasis> if the element was in
            the list, or <emphasis>False</emphasis> otherwise. For example:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> elem 2 [1,2,3,4,5]
True
Prelude> elem 6 [1,2,3,4,5]
False </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            The function <function>notElem</function> is exactly the inverse of
            <function>elem</function>, and returns <emphasis>True</emphasis> if
            an element is not in the list, and <emphasis>False</emphasis>
            otherwise:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> notElem "foo" ["foo","bar","baz"]
False
Prelude> notElem "pony" ["foo","bar","baz"]
True</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Ok, so we want to add an element to a list if, but only if, it is
            true that it is not yet a member of that list. Or in other words,
            the addition is conditional. Haskell provides a set of keywords to
            model conditionals, if..then..else. The structure is like this:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>if expr then a else b </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            This whole structure itself is an expression. This expression
            evaluates to <emphasis>a</emphasis> if <emphasis>expr</emphasis>
            evaluates to <emphasis>True</emphasis> or to <emphasis>b</emphasis>
            if <emphasis>expr</emphasis> evaluates to False. To give a working,
            but useless example:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> if 1 == 2 then "cuckoo" else "egg"
"egg"
Prelude> if 1 == 1 then "cuckoo" else "egg"
"cuckoo"</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            This looks exactly like what we need. Just fill in the blanks:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> if elem "foo" ["foo","bar","baz"] then ["foo","bar","baz"]
  else "foo" : ["foo", "bar", "baz"]
["foo","bar","baz"]
Prelude> if elem "pony" ["foo","bar","baz"] then ["foo","bar","baz"]
  else "pony" : ["foo", "bar", "baz"]
["pony","foo","bar","baz"]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            That's a bit contrived, but (as you hopefully see) not if we
            rewrite it to a function:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> let elemOrAdd e l = if elem e l then l else e:l
Prelude> elemOrAdd "foo" ["foo", "bar", "baz"]
["foo","bar","baz"]
Prelude> elemOrAdd "pony" ["foo", "bar", "baz"]
["pony","foo","bar","baz"]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Now we need to apply this to all words in a text, starting with an
            empty list. Haskell provides a function to do this, but brace
            yourself, the first time it may look a bit 'difficult'. It is named
            <function>foldl</function> (a so-called) left-fold. A left fold
            traverses a list from head to tail, applying a function to each
            element, just like <function>map</function>. However, the
            difference is that it can, but does not necessarily return a list.
            As such, it is a generalization of the <function>map</function>
            function. As usual, you can inspect the type signature to see the
            arguments of <function>foldl</function>:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type foldl
foldl :: (a -> b -> a) -> a -> [b] -> a</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Now consider this example using <function>foldl</function>:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> foldl (+) 0 [1,2,3,4,5]
15</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Stepwise, this fold is executed in the following manner:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>foldl (+) 0 [1,2,3,4,5]
foldl (+) ((0)+1) [2,3,4,5]
foldl (+) (((0)+1)+2) [3,4,5]
foldl (+) ((((0)+1)+2)+3) [4,5]
foldl (+) (((((0)+1)+2)+3)+4) [5]
foldl (+) ((((((0)+1)+2)+3)+4)+5)) []
((((((0)+1)+2)+3)+4)+5))</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            So, it works by applying a function to some initial argument
            (<emphasis>0</emphasis> in this case) as its first argument, and
            the first element of the list as its second argument. When
            processing the second element of the list, this expression is then
            the first argument of the function, and the second element is the
            second argument, etc. The first argument of the function that is
            applied is also called the <emphasis>accumulator</emphasis>, since
            it accumulates results up till that point.
        </para>
        <para>
            This could also work for our <function>elemOrAdd</function>
            function. Unfortunately, <function>elemOrAdd</function> requires
            the accumulator as the second argument, and the function passed to
            <function>foldl</function> as the first argument. Compare the type
            signatures:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type foldl
foldl :: (a -> b -> a) -> a -> [b] -> a
Prelude> :type elemOrAdd
elemOrAdd :: (Eq a) => a -> [a] -> [a]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            In the function that is the first argument to
            <function>foldl</function>, the return type is the same as the type
            of the first argument. In the case of
            <function>elemOrAdd</function>, the type of the second argument
            corresponds to that of the first. Of course, an easy 'hack' to
            solve this, is to redefine elemOrAdd, switching its arguments, and
            plug it into foldl:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> let elemOrAdd l e = if elem e l then l else e:l
Prelude> foldl elemOrAdd [] ["blue", "blue", "red", "blue", "red"]
["red","blue"]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Since we are building a list, we use the empty list
            (<emphasis>[]</emphasis>) as the initial accumulator for this fold.
            Stepwise, the fold works like this:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>foldl elemOrAdd [] ["blue", "blue", "red", "blue", "red"]
foldl elemOrAdd ("blue":([])) ["blue", "blue", "red", "blue", "red"]
foldl elemOrAdd ("blue":([])) ["blue", "red", "blue", "red"]
foldl elemOrAdd ("blue":([])) ["red", "blue", "red"]
foldl elemOrAdd ("red":("blue":([]))) ["blue", "red"]
foldl elemOrAdd ("red":("blue":([]))) ["red"]
foldl elemOrAdd ("red":("blue":([]))) []
("red":("blue":([])))
["red","blue"]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Now we wrap it up in another function, and you have constructed two
            functions that, together, make word lists:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> let wordList = foldl elemOrAdd []
Prelude> wordList ["blue", "blue", "red", "blue", "red"]
["red","blue"]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            While our little word list function works fine on small texts, it
            will not be very efficient for big corpora. The reason is simple -
            suppose that we have already found 100,000 different tokens. For
            every word, it would have to check the list of 100,000 tokens.
            There is no other way of doing this than to traverse the list word
            by word. Or, on average, we compare a token to 100,000 / 2 = 50,000
            elements in the list. As a computer scientist would say:
            <function>elemOrAdd</function> works in linear time, its processing
            time is linear to the number of different tokens that were seen.
        </para>
        <para>
            This is a typical case of picking the wrong data structure for the
            task. But for illustrative purposes, using lists was nice and
            simple. But since you are a working programmer, you want workable
            solutions. Bring in the sets! A set is, like the mathematical set,
            a collection that does not contain duplicate elements. That is
            good, because a word list does not contain duplicate elements.
            Silly us, we were fooled by the word <emphasis>list</emphasis>.
            What we actually want to build is a word set. It is just for
            historical purposes, people used paper in a long gone past, that it
            is called a word list.
        </para>
        <para>
            Another nice property of sets, as they are normally implemented, is
            that set membership can be checked rather quickly. In the sets that
            we will use, membership checking is in logarithmic time. Or in
            other words, if comparison took one second, we would on average
            need 50,000 seconds to search the list mentioned earlier, but only
            <emphasis>log(100,000)</emphasis> or approximately 11.5 seconds to
            check whether the element in in a set. Talking about optimizations!
        </para>
        <para>
            Haskell provides sets, but not in the so-called
            <emphasis>Prelude</emphasis>. <emphasis>Prelude</emphasis> is a
            module that contains functions. The <emphasis>Prelude</emphasis>
            module is always loaded, so its functions are always available
            (unless you explicitly ask Haskell to hide them). The functions
            <function>map</function>, <function>head</function>,
            <function>tail</function>, and <function>length</function>, for
            instance, are defined in the <emphasis>Prelude</emphasis>.
            Functions for set manipulation, on the other hand, are defined in a
            module named <emphasis>Data.Set</emphasis>. For the time being, we
            will access functions from modules by prefixing the name of the
            module. For instance, this will give us the empty set:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Data.Set.empty
fromList []</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Like a list, a set can contain elements of various types. We see
            this when inspecting the type signature of the
            <function>empty</function> function:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type Data.Set.empty
Data.Set.empty :: Data.Set.Set a</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            <function>empty</function> returns a Set of some type
            <emphasis>a</emphasis>. We can also construct a
            <emphasis>Set</emphasis> from a list using the
            <function>fromList</function> function:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Data.Set.fromList [5,2,5,8,1,1,23]
fromList [1,2,5,8,23]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            As you can see here, the set does not contain duplicates. Another
            nice property of Haskell sets is that they are ordered. We can also
            do the inverse, convert a set to a list using
            <function>toList</function>:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Data.Set.toList (Data.Set.fromList [5,2,5,8,1,1,23])
[1,2,5,8,23]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Elements can be added to or removed from a <emphasis>Set</emphasis>
            using respectively the <function>insert</function> and
            <function>delete</function> functions. Both functions return a set
            with that element inserted or removed:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Data.Set.insert 42 (Data.Set.fromList [5,2,5,8,1,1,23])
fromList [1,2,5,8,23,42]
Prelude> Data.Set.delete 5 (Data.Set.fromList [5,2,5,8,1,1,23])
fromList [1,2,8,23]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Finally, we can check whether some value is a member of a set by
            using the <function>member</function> function:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Data.Set.member 23 (Data.Set.fromList [5,2,5,8,1,1,23])
True
Prelude> Data.Set.member 24 (Data.Set.fromList [5,2,5,8,1,1,23])
False</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            We have now seen enough to change our word list function. Rather
            than checking whether a value is in a list and adding it if not, we
            check whether it is in a <emphasis>Set</emphasis> and add it if it
            is not:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> let elemOrAdd s e = if Data.Set.member e s then s else Data.Set.insert e s
Prelude> elemOrAdd (Data.Set.fromList [5,2,5,8,1,1,23]) 24
fromList [1,2,5,8,23,24]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            That was simple. But it feels a weird, right? The most vital
            characteristic of a set is that it never contains duplicate
            elements, why do we need to check for duplicates? We don't. So,
            forget about <function>elemOrAdd</function>, we will only use
            <emphasis>Data.Set.insert</emphasis> from this point. Our objective
            now is to traverse a list of tokens, adding each token to a set,
            starting with the empty set. Our first take is this:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> let wordSet = foldl Data.Set.insert Data.Set.empty</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            However, this will not work. Remember that in the function we give
            to <function>foldl</function>, the accumulator has to be the first
            argument? We are accumulating a <emphasis>Set</emphasis>, but the
            set is the second argument to <emphasis>Data.Set.insert</emphasis>.
            We will pull a little trick out of our hat.
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> let wordSet = foldl (\s e -> Data.Set.insert e s) Data.Set.empty </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            You might be thinking &quot;Oh, no, more syntax terror! Does it
            ever stop?&quot; Actually,
            <emphasis>( e -&gt; Data.Set.insert e s)</emphasis> is very
            familiar. You could see it as an inline function. In functional
            programming jargon, this is called a <emphasis>lambda</emphasis>.
            Check out the type signature of the lambda:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type (\s e -> Data.Set.insert e s)
(\s e -> Data.Set.insert e s)
  :: (Ord a) => Data.Set.Set a -> a -> Data.Set.Set a</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            It is just a function, it takes a set of some type
            <emphasis>a</emphasis>, a value of type <emphasis>a</emphasis>, and
            returns <emphasis>a</emphasis>. The lambda has two arguments that
            are bound to <emphasis>s</emphasis> and <emphasis>e</emphasis>. The
            function body comes after the arrow. To emphasize that this is just
            a function, the following functions are equivalent:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>myFun = (\s e -> Data.Set.insert e s)
myFun s e = Data.Set.insert e ss </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Back to our <function>wordSet</function> function. We used the
            lambda to swap the arguments of
            <emphasis>Data.Set.insert</emphasis>.
            <emphasis>Data.Set.insert</emphasis> takes a value and a set, our
            lambda takes a set and a value. The rest of the function follows
            the same pattern as <emphasis>wordList</emphasis>, except that we
            start with an empty set rather than an empty list. The function
            works as expected:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> wordSet ["blue", "blue", "red", "blue", "red"]
fromList ["blue","red"]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            You have done it! You are now not only able to make a function that
            creates a word list, but also one that is performant.
        </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Exercises</title>
            <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
                <listitem>
                    <para> To measure the vocabulary of a writer, a so-called type-token ratio can
                        be calculated. This is the number of different tokens occurring in a text
                        (so-called 'types') divided by the number of tokens in that text. For
                        instance the phrase &quot;to be or not to be&quot; contains six tokens and
                        four types (<emphasis>to</emphasis>, <emphasis>be</emphasis>,
                        <emphasis>or</emphasis>, <emphasis>not</emphasis>). The type-token ratio
                        of this phrase is <emphasis>4 / 6 = 2 / 3</emphasis>.</para>
                    <para>Write a function that calculates the type-token ratio of a list of tokens.
                        You can use the <emphasis>Data.Set.size</emphasis> function to get the
                        number of elements in a set. </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-words-source-file">
        <title>Storing functions in a file</title>
        <para>
            Now that we are writing longer and longer functions, it becomes
            more convenient to define functions in a file rather than the
            <emphasis role="bold">ghci</emphasis> prompt. You can do this by
            creating a file using a plain-text editor with the
            <emphasis>.hs</emphasis> extension. Functions can be written down
            in the same manner as in <emphasis>ghci</emphasis>, but without the
            preceding <emphasis>let</emphasis> keyword. It is also highly
            recommended to add a type signature before the function. Haskell
            will check the function against the type signature, and report an
            error if they do not correspond. This will help you catch incorrect
            function definitions.
        </para>
        <para>
            The <function>palindrome</function> function discussed earlier in
            this chapter can be written to a file like this:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>palindrome :: (Eq a) => [a] -> Bool
palindrome word = word == reverse word </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            If you saved this file as <emphasis>chapter2.hs</emphasis>, you can
            load it in <emphasis role="bold">ghci</emphasis> using the
            <emphasis>:l</emphasis> (shorthand for <emphasis>:load</emphasis>)
            command:
        </para>
            <programlisting>Prelude> :l chapter1
[1 of 1] Compiling Main             ( chapter1.hs, interpreted )
Ok, modules loaded: Main.
*Main> palindrome "racecar"
True </programlisting>
        <para>
            For code fragments that use a module other than the prelude, add an
            import statement at the top of the file. For example, the
            <function>wordSet</function> function from the previous section
            should be saved to a text file in the following manner:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting>import qualified Data.Set

wordSet :: Ord a => [a] -> Data.Set.Set a
wordSet = foldl (\s e -> Data.Set.insert e s) Data.Set.empty </programlisting>
        <para>
            From now on, we assume that examples are written to a text file,
            except when the <emphasis>Prelude&gt;</emphasis> occurs in the
            example.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-words-freq-list">
        <title>Word frequency lists</title>
        <para>
            The word list function that we built in the previous section works
            is useful for various tasks, like calculating the type-token ratio
            for a text. For some other tasks this is not good enough - we want
            to be able to find out how often a word was used. We can expand a
            word list with frequencies to make a
            <emphasis>word frequency list</emphasis>.
        </para>
        <para>
            To be able to store word frequencies, every word has to be
            associated with an integer. We could store such an association as a
            tuple. A tuple is a data type with a fixed number of elements and a
            fixed type for an element. Examples of tuples are:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    (1,2,3)
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    (&quot;hello&quot;,&quot;world&quot;)
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    (&quot;hello&quot;,1)
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            As you can see, they differ from lists in that they can have values
            of different types as elements. However, if you inspect the type
            signatures of these tuples, you will see that the length and type
            for each position is fixed:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type (1,2,3)
(1,2,3) :: (Num t, Num t1, Num t2) => (t, t1, t2)
Prelude> :type ("hello","world")
("hello","world") :: ([Char], [Char])
Prelude> :type ("hello",1)
("hello",1) :: (Num t) => ([Char], t) </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            To store frequencies, we could use a list of tuples of the type
            <emphasis>[([Char], Int)]</emphasis>. The phrase &quot;to be or not
            to be&quot; could be stored as
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>[("to",2),("be",2),("or",1),("not",1)]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            However, this would be even less efficient than using lists for
            constructing word lists. First, like <function>elemOrAdd</function>
            we would potentially have to search the complete list to locate a
            word. Second, we would have to reconstruct the list up to the point
            of the element. In the <function>elemOrAdd</function> function we
            could just give the list a new head, but now we would have to
            replace the element to update the word frequency and add all
            preceding list items again. Since Haskell is a 'pure' language, we
            cannot modify existing values.
        </para>
        <para>
            A more appropriate data type for this task is a map (not to be
            confused with the <function>map</function> function). A map maps a
            key to a value. In Haskell, maps are provided in the
            <emphasis>Data.Map</emphasis> module. Like sets, we can make an
            empty map:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Data.Map.empty fromList
[]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            When you inspect the type signature of the empty map, you can see
            that it parametrizes over two types, a type for the key and a type
            for values:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type Data.Map.empty
Data.Map.empty :: Data.Map.Map k a </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            We can construct a <emphasis>Map</emphasis> from a list of binary
            tuples (tuples with two elements), where the first element of the
            tuple becomes the key, and the second the value:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Data.Map.fromList [("to",2),("be",2),("or",1),("not",1)]
fromList [("be",2),("not",1),("or",1),("to",2)]
Prelude> :type Data.Map.fromList [("to",2),("be",2),("or",1),("not",1)]
Data.Map.fromList [("to",2),("be",2),("or",1),("not",1)]
  :: (Num t) => Data.Map.Map [Char] t</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            This also binds the types for the map: we are mapping from keys of
            type string to values of type t that belongs to the
            <emphasis>t</emphasis> typeclass. No specific value for types is
            used (yet), because the numbers could be integers or fractionals.
        </para>
        <para>
            The <function>insert</function> function is used to add a new
            mapping to the <emphasis>Map</emphasis>. If a mapping with the
            given key already exists, the existing mapping is replaced:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Data.Map.insert "hello" 1 (Data.Map.fromList [("to",2),("be",2),("or",1),("not",1)])
fromList [("be",2),("hello",1),("not",1),("or",1),("to",2)]
Prelude> Data.Map.insert "be" 1 (Data.Map.fromList [("to",2),("be",2),("or",1),("not",1)])
fromList [("be",1),("not",1),("or",1),("to",2)]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Looking up values is a bit peculiar. You can lookup a value with
            the <function>lookup</function> function. However, if you inspect
            the type signature, you will see that the value is not returned as
            is:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> :type Data.Map.lookup
Data.Map.lookup :: (Ord k) => k -> Data.Map.Map k a -> Maybe a</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Rather than returning a value, it returns the value packed in some
            box called <emphasis>Maybe</emphasis>. <emphasis>Maybe a</emphasis>
            is a type that has just two possible so-called
            <emphasis>constructors</emphasis>, <emphasis>Just a</emphasis> or
            <emphasis>Nothing</emphasis>. You can put your own values in a
            <emphasis>Maybe</emphasis> box using the
            <emphasis>Just a</emphasis> constructor:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Just 22
Just 22
Prelude> :type Just 22
Just 22 :: (Num t) => Maybe t
Prelude> Just [1,2,3,4,5]
Just [1,2,3,4,5]
Prelude> Just "stay calm"
Just "stay calm"
Prelude> :type Just "stay calm"
Just "stay calm" :: Maybe [Char]</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            You can also make a box that contains vast emptiness with the
            <emphasis>Nothing</emphasis> constructor:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Nothing
Nothing
Prelude> :type Nothing
Nothing :: Maybe a </screen>
        </para>
        <para> These boxes turn out to be pretty cool: you can use them to return something or
            nothing from functions, without resorting to all kinds of abominations as exceptions or
            null pointers (if you never heard of exceptions or pointers, do not worry, you have a
            life full of bliss). Since <emphasis>Maybe</emphasis> is so nice, the
                <function>lookup</function> function uses it. It will return the value packed with
            in a <emphasis>Just</emphasis> constructor if the key occurred in the map, or <emphasis
                role="italic">Nothing</emphasis> otherwise: </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Data.Map.lookup "to" (Data.Map.fromList [("to",2),("be",2),("or",1),("not",1)])
Just 2
Prelude> Data.Map.lookup "wrong" (Data.Map.fromList [("to",2),("be",2),("or",1),("not",1)])
Nothing </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            As for handling these values - we will come to that later. Mappings
            are deleted from a <emphasis>Map</emphasis> by key with the
            <function>delete</function> function. If a key did not occur in the
            <emphasis>Map</emphasis>, the original map is returned:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Data.Map.delete "to" (Data.Map.fromList [("to",2),("be",2),("or",1),("not",1)])
fromList [("be",2),("not",1),("or",1)]
Prelude> Data.Map.delete "wrong" (Data.Map.fromList [("to",2),("be",2),("or",1),("not",1)])</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Finally, a <emphasis>Map</emphasis> can be converted to a list
            using the <function>toList</function> function:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>Prelude> Data.Map.toList (Data.Map.fromList [("to",2),("be",2),("or",1),("not",1)])
[("be",2),("not",1),("or",1),("to",2)]</screen>
        </para>
        <para> Alright. Back to our task at hand: constructing a word frequency list. As with word
            lists, we want to traverse a list of words, accumulating data. So, the use of
                <function>foldl</function> is a appropriate for this task. During each folding step,
            we take the <emphasis role="italic">Map</emphasis> created in a previous step. We then
            lookup the value for the current step in the <emphasis role="italic">Map</emphasis>. If
            it does not exist, we add it to the <emphasis role="italic">Map</emphasis> giving it a
            frequency of one. Otherwise, we want to increase the frequency by one. The
                <function>countElem</function> function does this: </para>

            <programlisting>import qualified Data.Map

countElem :: (Ord k) => Data.Map.Map k Int -> k -> Data.Map.Map k Int
countElem m e = case (Data.Map.lookup e m) of
                  Just v  -> Data.Map.insert e (v + 1) m
                  Nothing -> Data.Map.insert e 1 m</programlisting>
        <para>This function introduces the <emphasis role="italic">case</emphasis> construct.
            Remember that <function>lookup</function> uses the nify <emphasis role="italic"
                >Maybe</emphasis> data type? The <emphasis role="italic">case</emphasis> construct
            allows us to select an expression based on a constructor. If <function>lookup</function>
            returned a value using the <emphasis role="italic">Just</emphasis> constructor, the key
            was in the <emphasis role="italic">Map</emphasis>. In this case, we bind the value to
            the name <emphasis role="italic">v</emphasis> and add a new value for this key. This
            value is the old value for this key incremented by one. If a value with the <emphasis
                role="italic">Nothing</emphasis> constructor was returned, the key was not in the
                <emphasis role="italic">Map</emphasis>. So, we will add it, and give it a
            (frequency) value of 1.</para>
        <para>The <function>countElem</function> function works as intended:</para>
        <screen>*Main> foldl countElem Data.Map.empty ["to","be","or","not","to","be"]
fromList [("be",2),("not",1),("or",1),("to",2)]</screen>
        <para>While this was a nice exercise, the <emphasis role="italic"
                >Data.Map.insertWith</emphasis> function can drastically shorten our function. This
            function uses an update function to update a value, or a specified value if the key is
            not present in the <emphasis role="italic">Map</emphasis>. The update function gets the
            specified value as its first argument, and the old value as its second argument. Using
                <function>insertWith</function>, we can shorten our function to:</para>
        <programlisting language="haskell">countElem :: (Ord k) => Data.Map.Map k Int -> k -> Data.Map.Map k Int
countElem m e = Data.Map.insertWith (\n o -> n + o) e 1 m</programlisting>
        <para>If an element was not seen in the <emphasis role="italic">Map</emphasis> yet, a
            frequency of 1 will be inserted. If the element does occur as a key in the map, the
            lambda adds one to the old frequency. With <function>countElem</function> in our reach,
            we can define the <function>freqList</function> function:</para>
        <programlisting language="haskell">freqList :: (Ord k) => [k] -> Data.Map.Map k Int
freqList = foldl countElem Data.Map.empty</programlisting>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-words-read-text-corpus">
        <title>Reading a text corpus</title>
        <para> Stub: read files, apply freqList to a corpus, Zipfian distribution.</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
