<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="chap-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-intro-welcome">
        <title>Welcome</title>
        <para>Stub</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-intro-whats-nlp">
        <title>What is natural language processing?</title>
        <para>Stub</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-intro-whats-haskell">
        <title>What is Haskell?</title>
        <para>Haskell is a static, pure, lazy, functional language. Gee, that sounds an awful lot
            like buzzword lingo! That may well be, but these properties make Haskell a very
            effective language, and sometimes a bit odd. These properties are also opposite to most
            mainstream languages. For instance, Java is static, impure, eager, and not functional,
            Ruby is dynamic, impure, eager, and only functional at times. While it is hard to give
            an accurate definition of every characteristic, we will try anyway.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Functional:</emphasis> Haskell puts an emphasis on functions and
            treats computation as the evaluation of functions. This in contrast to so-called
            imperative languages, that specify an order of instructions. As such, Haskell functions
            very often resemble mathematical functions closely. Being functional also has practical
            implications. For instance, iteration is accomplished by means of recursion, and
            functions are also values and can be passed to other functions.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Pure:</emphasis> Haskell is a pure language, in that functions
            do not have side-effects. This means that existing values cannot be changed, since
            changing data would be a side-effect of a function. It also guarantees that the
            evaluation of a function will always result in the same value given the same function
            arguments.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Lazy:</emphasis> As a lazy language, Haskell only evaluates
            expressions when needed. Say you just implemented a function that gives a list of all
            prime numbers. In a strict language, the function that makes the list will never
            terminate (since there are always more prime numbers). Haskell, on the contrary, will
            only evaluate this function when and as much as necessary. As long as you take a finite
            number of primes from the list, the program will happily terminate.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Static:</emphasis> Haskell programs are compiled before they can
            run. This means that the Haskell compiler will catch many errors for you at
            compile-time, rather than finding them when your program is used in production.
            Additionally, Haskell does <emphasis role="italic">type-inference</emphasis>. This means
            that the Haskell compiler can find out the types of values most of the times, and you do
            not need to type-annotate every value.</para>
        <para>If you have prior programming experience in an imperative or eager language, Haskell
            can feel a bit odd in the beginning. Don't worry, you will feel warm and fuzzy
            eventually!</para>
        <para>You may ask why we chose Haskell as the main programming language for this book,
            rather than a more mainstream language. During our own experiences developing natural
            language processing tools, we noticed that very many natural language processing tasks
            are relatively straightforward data transformations. Haskell is a language that is
            exceptionally good at data transformations. First of all, because it has <emphasis
                role="italic">higher order functions</emphasis> (functions that take functions as an
            argument) that traverse lists, sets, mappings, etc. Second, Haskell makes it easy to
            construct more complex transformations out of simple transformations.</para>
        <para>Although this book does not provide a full introduction to the Haskell programming
            language, we try to cover Haskell concepts extensively when required. If you require
            more background on certain concepts, we recommend you to consult the book <emphasis
                role="italic" xlink:href="http://learnyouahaskell.com/">Learn Haskell for Great
                Good!</emphasis></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-intro-needs">
        <title>What you need</title>
        <para>To work with this book, you need the Haskell Platform and a text editor. The Haskell
            Platform is available for Mac OS X, Windows, and Linux at: <link
                xlink:href="http://hackage.haskell.org/platform/"
                >http://hackage.haskell.org/platform/</link> Download the package for your platform,
            and install it.</para>
        <para>If you do not use one of these platforms, not all is lost. First of all, you should
            download the <package>ghc</package> Haskell compiler. If you operating system provides a
            ports system or package manager, use it to locate and install a <package>ghc</package>
            package. If your operating system does not provide a port or package for
                <package>ghc</package>, you can still try to download a binary distribution from
                <link xlink:href="http://www.haskell.org/ghc/">the GHC website</link>. Once you have
            installed and set up <package>ghc</package>, install the packages of the Haskell
            Platform.</para>
        <para>For the text editor, pick any editor you find comfortable, as long as it saves files
            as plain text. Programming Haskell becomes more comfortable if you have an editor with
            syntax highlighting and interpreter integration. Your authors prefer the Emacs editor
            with haskell-mode. haskell-mode provides good support for highlighting, and Haskell code
            formatting. Besides that, Emacs allows you to run the <command>ghci</command> Haskell
            interpreter within the editor.</para>
        <para>Some examples in the book use corpora. These corpora are available at: <link
                xlink:href="http://nlpwp.org/">http://nlpwp.org/</link></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Ready, set, go!</title>
        <para>You will probably want to get aquainted with the <command>ghci</command> Haskell
            interpreter. It allows you to try Haskell expressions and get immediate feedback. On
            UNIX systems, type <command>ghci -XNoMonomorphismRestriction</command> in a terminal to
            launch the interpreter. You will be greeted with a prompt that resembles the
            following:<screen>$ <userinput>ghci -XNoMonomorphismRestriction</userinput>
GHCi, version 6.12.3: http://www.haskell.org/ghc/  :? for help
Loading package ghc-prim ... linking ... done.
Loading package integer-gmp ... linking ... done.
Loading package base ... linking ... done.
Loading package ffi-1.0 ... linking ... done.
Prelude></screen>
            On Windows, choose <emphasis role="italic">Start -> All Programs -> Haskell Platform ->
                WinGHCi</emphasis>. The first time, you should set the <emphasis role="italic"
                >NoMonomorphismRestriction</emphasis> option that is required for some examples. Do
            this by going to the following item: <emphasis role="italic">File > Options > GHCi
                Startup</emphasis>. Then append <emphasis role="italic"
                >-XNoMonomorphismRestriction</emphasis> in the field (make sure that there is a
            space before this addition). Click <emphasis role="italic">OK</emphasis>, and restart
            WinGHCi.</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
